<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The improvement of mercy: or a short treatise, shewing how, and in what manner, our rulers and all well-affected to the present government should make a right and profitable use of the late great victory in Ireland. August 2. 1649. Also here are severall things propounded to all such as are dis-affected and enemies to the state (whether Presbyterian, Royalist, or Papist, &amp;c.) beeing both usefull and seasonable upon this occasion, of so wonderfull and glorious a victorie. / By John Canne. Published by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E571_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859672</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859672</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165354</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79838)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165354)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 88:E571[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The improvement of mercy: or a short treatise, shewing how, and in what manner, our rulers and all well-affected to the present government should make a right and profitable use of the late great victory in Ireland. August 2. 1649. Also here are severall things propounded to all such as are dis-affected and enemies to the state (whether Presbyterian, Royalist, or Papist, &amp;c.) beeing both usefull and seasonable upon this occasion, of so wonderfull and glorious a victorie. / By John Canne. Published by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons in Aldersgate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Cambridge University Library (Early English Books) and the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mercy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165354:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IMPROVEMENT OF MERCY: <hi>OR</hi> A ſhort Treatiſe, ſhewing how, and in what manner, Our <hi>RULERS</hi> and all <hi>well-affected</hi> to the <hi>preſent Government</hi> ſhould make a right and profitable uſe of the late great Victory in <hi>Ireland. Auguſt</hi> 2. 1649. <hi>ALSO</hi> Here are ſeverall things propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all ſuch as are diſ-affected and enemies to the State (whether <hi>Presbyterian, Royaliſt,</hi> or <hi>Papiſt,</hi> &amp;c.) Beeing both uſefull and ſeaſonable <hi>upon this occaſion, of ſo wonderfull and glorious a Victorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> JOHN CANNE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod. 15.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Who is like unto thee, O Lord, amongst the Gods? Who is like thee? glorious in holineſſe, fearfull in praiſes, doing wonders!</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 32.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For their Rock is not as our Rock, even our enemies themſelves being Judges.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons</hi> in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreete.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:165354:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165354:2"/>
            <head>THE IMPROVEMENT OF MERCY: <hi>OR</hi> A ſhort Treatiſe, ſhewing how, and in what manner, our Rulers and all well-affected to the preſent Government ſhould make a right and profitable uſe of the late great Victory in <hi>Ireland. Auguſt</hi> 2. 1649.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been the cuſtome of men in former time, as we finde it recorded, both in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and humane Hiſtory: when the Lord had given them any remarkeable and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall victory, to erect ſome great <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> whereby the Remembrance of ſuch a <hi>Mercy</hi> might continue from Generation to Generation.</p>
            <p>As I conſider our late <hi>victory</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> how wonderfull it was, and how ſeaſonably God gave that bleſſing to us, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances; I finde my ſpirit much let out, to move and deſire, that ſome thing now may be done by this Nation (who enjoyes the fruit of that happie harveſt) to keep up the memory of it, that our Poſteritie hereafter may know, what the Lord did for us at ſuch a time, and may ſay, <hi>Wee have heard with our eares, O God, our fathers have told us, what work thou didſt in their dayes, in the times of old,</hi> Pſal. 44.1.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165354:3"/>
            <p>And I am the more encouraged to take this work in hand, and have the greater hope, that <hi>England</hi> will be an example to the whole world, of minding Gods providence, and improving this mercy, becauſe no Nation like <hi>England</hi> for many yeeres, hath had ſo large experience of GODS power and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>And that I may the better obtaine the thing ſo much deſired, I ſhall in an humble and ſubmiſſive way; firſt propound a few things to the State. My Lords, I need not tell you, how much you are concerned in this Victory: What an Intereſt you have in it; I know you doe obſerve how wonderfully herein God hath honoured you, owned your preſent Government, and don more for you, then was expected. But now what will yee render to the Lord for ſo great a benefit toward you? What <hi>Pillar</hi> or <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of Praiſe</hi> will you erect to continue the memory of this Victory. I ſhall not take upon mee to preſcribe the particulare, nevertheleſſe, it cannot be thought either preſumption or bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in mee, if I deliver mine own opinion, and ſet down what I humbly conceive, will be a fit <hi>Monument;</hi> acceptable to God, honourable to you, and whereby your names ſhall be a bleſſing to poſteritie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Seeing the Lord hath ſo really appeared to enlarge and eſtabliſh your Common-wealth, is it not fit that you ſhould be as reall for him in advancing the glorious Kingdome of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. There have been ſeverall Petitions preſented to the Parliament, from many godly and well affected people, whoſe bowels doe earne to conſider, what multitudes of people ſit ſtill in darkneſſe, and have not the glorious Goſpel preached unto them. Thankes indeed they had, and faire promiſes: now wee know a man may draw a thouſand prints in water, but as ſoone as his finger is off, all is out. Sirs; our hope is, that you will now doe ſomething effectually towards the ſalvation of ſuch ignorant and poore ſoules.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It will manifeſt both your acknowledgement and improvement of this mercy, if you honour ſuch, whom God hath ſo farre honoured, as by them to bring over ſeverall Victories to you. When tydings was brought to <hi>Philip of Macedon:</hi> 1. that <hi>Parmenio</hi> had got the victory over the enemies. 2. <hi>Alexander</hi> his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165354:3"/>Son was borne. 3. That his Chariots won the priz: at <hi>Olympus;</hi> and all in one day; he call'd for ſome croſſe, that theſe things might not make him forget himſelfe: howſoever, we wiſh you no croſſes, but increaſe of bleſſings, and all good things, yet withall wee deſire, that what ſucceſſe ſoever God gives you, you may not ſo farre forget your ſelves, as to forget your friends, ſuch as have ever been cordiall and faithfull to you, carried their lives in their hands for you, and thought nothing too deare for your ſake.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In this victory you may behold Gods diſpleaſure againſt Malignants, he will not take them by the hand, neither ſhould you into your boſome. Is the Lord pulling of them downe, be not you then ſetting of them up. If a ſpider can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile ſo much as come into the hive and weave a cobweb within it, he will kill all the bees, there is no remedy. We hope you will take care to keepe ſuch ſpiders out: to wit, of place and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the Common-wealth. We would count him unwiſe, that would feed rats, miſe, and ſuch vermine, to deſtroy his bodily eſtate; but it is greater folly to nouriſh ſuch as ſeek to deſtroy the Nation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Hath the Lord compaſſed you about with ſongs of deliverance, and filled your hearts with joy and gladneſſe; doe ſomething now for the people, I mean ſome remarkeable thing, that ſo by you they may be glad and rejoyce likewiſe. I need not tell you whoſe hearts are ſad, nor why, and what would comfort them: open but a dore to them, and heare what they would ſay, how many weeks and moneths ſome have waited, and can finde no way or paſſage to have their heavy condition and caſe come before you. It would therefore be a notable <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument</hi> to continue the memory of this <hi>Victorie,</hi> if ſome preſent courſe were taken, that the caſe of the poore and friendleſſe might be heard as ſoon as others; and people not ſuffer ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely as they doe, in that their buſineſſes are not ſpeedier diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> thought that day ill ſpent, in which he had not holpen ſome <hi>poore perſon:</hi> Mark that, (not <hi>himſelfe,</hi> not his brother or ſiſter, not ſuch a Lord or Lady, &amp;c. but the poore who had no friends,) conſider hee was a Heathen, you are Chriſtians.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165354:4"/>
            <p>Fiftly, <hi>Dublins Enlargement</hi> may ſerve to put you in minde of the poore priſoners for debt: I know you have ſpent ſome time about this buſineſſe, but I pray conſider with what celeritie and quickneſſe, God did that great work in <hi>Ireland</hi> for you: and therefore you ſhall doe well to follow God, as in matter, ſo in the manner of doing good. <hi>Say not unto thy neighbour, goe, and come againe, and to morrow I will give, when thou haſt it by thee,</hi> Pro. 3.28. <hi>Jam quando ſuppetit, quid probibet, quo mini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter impertiare? Nonne inops adeſt? Nonne plena horrea? Nonne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces à domino parata? Nonne mandatum manifeſtum? Eſuriens fame abſumitur, nudus frigore rigeſcit, &amp; tu eleemoſynam in craſtinum differs?</hi> Baſil. homil. 6. ex varijs.</p>
            <p>Among ſuch as are well affected to this preſent Government, I have thought good to mention the Lord <hi>Major</hi> of the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> with the Court of Aldermen, and Common Councell. I know you are much affected with this Victory, judging it one of the greateſt Mercies, that ever God gave to his Church and people in this Nation. And it being ſo, I hope then we ſhall have ſome Monument erected by you for a memoriall of ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable bleſſing, fit to be transferred to future poſterities. Wee ſee in nature when the Sunne ſhines upon thoſe inferior bodies, if ſolid bodies, when they reflect their beames, they caſt their light and heat upon other bodies that are neereſt about them: but if they are empty and hollow bodies, and ſuch as have no ſoliditie, they take all into themſelves, and reflect not. The Lord by this victory hath in a ſpeciall manner ſhined on your City, on your families, callings, eſtates; bleſt you in curſing the enemy. Now in charitie I am bound to beleeve, that you are men ſolid, ſincere: and as the Moone taking light from the Sunne above her, beſtoweth it upon the creatures here below, ſo you will make others partakers of the good bleſſings of God beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon you. And here I ſhall deſire with your leave and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to propound a few things briefly to you, as the <hi>uſe</hi> of this victory in relation to your Citie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As God hath been zealous for you, ſo be you zealous of his glory and name. 2. Let there not onely be kept dayes of feaſting, and joy, and of ſending portions one to another, and gifts to the poore: but let ſomething now be don for the poore,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165354:4"/>and in ſuch a way, as the victory may be remembred in all ages hereafter. 3. Let the Army be ſtill deare and precious to you: for Gods preſence (you ſee) is amongſt them whereſoever they are: and whether they are <hi>Engliſh, Scots,</hi> or <hi>Iriſh,</hi> which come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they are bread for them, God ſcatters their enemies, and they fly before them. Who would be unwilling to give wages and large recompence unto ſervants who are faithfull, proſperous, profitable? 4. The conſideration of this victorie may encourage you, to hold your own, and ſtand faſt to the Parliament, Councell of State, and the preſent Government, and not to feare the ſecret plots and deſignes of the adverſary, neither their number nor forces. Let them aſſociate themſelves, and they ſhall be broken; take counſel together, and it ſhall come to nought; ſpeak the word, and it ſhall not ſtand: for God is with us. 5. Methinkes this Victory ſhould move you to be now very active in ſuppreſſing lewd and ſcandalous Pamphlets, and that roguiſh generation of Ballad ſingers, ſuch varlets were not ſuffered in many Heathen-Common-wealths, and truly it is much to be wiſhed, that more diligence and greater ſeveritie were uſed to remove from your Citie and ſuburbs, theſe baſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, viler then the earth.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, We ſhall expect now, as a proper improvement of this victory, that you will no longer ſuffer in your City <hi>Pulpit-Incendiaries,</hi> men who turn praying and preaching into rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As for their aſperſing the wayes of God and his people, wee let it paſſe (as the fruit whereby they are known to be —) But to heare them revile the Rulers of the people, and to ſpeake trayterouſly againſt the preſent Government, it is unſufferable. <hi>A Magiſtrate</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>who hath diſcovered a Conſpiracie, and ſeemes fearfull to remedie it, is as faultie as the Conſpirator himſelfe.</hi> But here is no cauſe of feare, the thing now may be eaſily reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died without any danger, or difficultie. Wee ſee the bladder is puft up with a little winde, and if two or three beanes or peaſe be put into it, they make a mighty ſound or ratling, yet prick the ſame but with a pin, and inſtantly it falls flat, and comes to nought: I leave the application and uſe to your ſelves: onely take notice, that in Chriſtian policie; <hi>Init<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſeditionum, quampri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum apparuerint comprimantur.</hi> Clem. Templ. pol. lib. 4. c. 7. p. 424.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:165354:5"/>
            <p>For the reſt of the Nation, who are well affected to the State, to the end they may make a profitable and good uſe of this great victory, I ſhall ſet down before them theſe obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. About the time that the Lord ſcattered his enemies, they were boaſting what they would doe with the <hi>Round-heads and Sectaries:</hi> Into <hi>England</hi> they ſhould not goe: <hi>Ormond</hi> as he was playing at Tables ſwore, he would ſend them all into <hi>America:</hi> Another in his cups vowed, he would try if they could ſwim thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>The enemy ſaid, I will purſue, I will overtake, I will divide the ſpoile: my luſt ſhall be ſatisfied upon them: I will draw my ſword, mine hand ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> Now no ſooner were theſe words out of their mouth, but the wrath of God fell immediately upon them, and they were all, either ſlaine, taken, or put to flight. <hi>So let thine enemies periſh, O God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If we conſider, the ſeverall advantages of the enemy, as their number, place, proviſion, and other circumſtances; and how not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they were totally routed, it is matter ſufficient, to perſwade every rationall man, to believe, that God was an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to them, and to the cauſe they ſtood for, and that he owned the others, by an unheard of victory and deliverance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In this victory we may behold a full victory over the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, both there, and here, and elſe where: For as ſoon as they heard of this thing, their hearts melted, &amp; ſuch a terrour is fallen upon them, as they have no minde to engage againe, nor to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute any more their new plots and deſignes againſt this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Upon the Affaires of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the enemies to this State much depended: it was indeed as the great Wheel of the Clock: For many made full account to <hi>move</hi> here, if the Rebels there prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. But as its ſaid, <hi>Many of the people of the Land became Jewes, for the feare of the Jewes fell upon them:</hi> ſo this victory in all places where it comes, brings people over to the Parliament, as well knowing, it is their beſt and ſafeſt courſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That five thouſand men, ſhould take and kill ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and put thirteen thouſand to flight, who ſees not that it is the immediate finger of God. And it is worth the obſerving, that ſince this later Army was raiſed, God hath given us many ſuch wonderfull victories: not onely for the comfort and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165354:5"/>of the well-affected, but to let the enemy ſee, that God is againſt them, and that they ſhall never proſper in ſuch a way. <hi>When thy judgements are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world will learne righteouſneſſe,</hi> Iſa. 26.9.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Here we may obſerve, Gods revenging hand upon Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates; not to ſpeake of <hi>Inchequeen,</hi> that <hi>Grand turn-coat,</hi> there were in <hi>Ormonds</hi> Army many Souldiers who had baſely and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly a little before deſerted the Parliaments ſervice: but ſee how the Lord dealt with them for their perfidiouſneſſe: he delivers them up into the hand of Juſtice. A faire warning to others, to take heed, that they keep themſelves with that partie where they ſee God is, and ſtill crownes with victory, and not to joyn with a rebellious rout, who have not his preſence, but are forſaken of him, and prepared for the day of ſlaughter.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whereas we heare of ſome unclean ſpirits, like frogs, going forth unto the Kings of the earth, to gather them to battle againſt this Common-wealth: there is ſo much of God to be ſeen in this victorie, as that no man needs to regard, whatſoever is reported concerning this thing. When other Nations ſhall heare how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully the Lord goes along with us in the work of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is probable they will keepe at home, and ſeeke to pull their necks out of the yoke of Tyrants, as we have don. But howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, we ſhall never hereafter be afraid of multitudes, the number ſhall not fright us: for we are confident, upon the experience of former victories, that God will ſtill make good that promiſe and bleſſing to us; <hi>Five of you ſhall chaſe an hundred: and an hundred of you ſhall put ten thouſand to flight; and your enemies ſhall fall before you by the ſword,</hi> Deut. 28.8.</p>
            <p>From the well-affected to the State, I come now to the ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected: and firſt to you of the <hi>Presbyterian partie:</hi> And here that I may not be miſtaken, I onely intend ſuch men, as doe vilifie and reproach our preſent Government. And as for ſuch wee have thought good from the occaſion of this victory, to frame ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like <hi>a looking-Glaſſe,</hi> wherein they may ſee themſelves; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at ſuch times, when inſtead of preaching the doctrine of the Goſpel, and praying in the Spirit, they ſpeake falſe, ſcandalous, and ſeditious things, tending to a new warre, and hindering the reliefe of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:165354:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, <hi>England</hi> hath received a mercy, in ſpight of you: you may remember the other day in your talke (I dare not call it prayer) how you told the Lord <hi>you knew not into whoſe hands to pray Ireland: onely you would not, that he ſhould give it up into the bands of the Independents.</hi> Beſides, wee are not ignorant, how proudly you contemnd Authoritie, and when others ſought the Lord for <hi>Ireland,</hi> you moſt prophanely and irreligiouſly, like <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and the King ſate down to drink:</hi> you made it a time of feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, joy, and gladneſſe, when others by Commandement kept a day of publick faſt: not unlike to that in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12, 13. Behold now, we have a returne of our prayers, our petition is granted, and the Lord hath look'd on our teares, and the Lord hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited good for your curſing that day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You have ſtrugled a long time to deſtroy this preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but doe yee not ſee now, how yee kick againſt the prick: As he that moves the weik of a burning Candle with his finger, blacks it, and burnes it, and cauſeth the light to ſhine the more cleare: So all your mutinous and ſeditious attempts, turne to the burning and blacking of your ſelves. As for the State, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by you, Loe it ſhines more and more in ſtrength, glory, and beautie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But whither will ye run? doe you not ſee how you are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fallen? here is a victory, one of the greateſt mercies that ever God brought from <hi>Ireland</hi> over to this Nation; nevertheleſſe, you ſee it not; nor thought it worth thankeſgiving in your Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the other day. Some report of the <hi>Manna,</hi> that at firſt it was ſweet and taſted well, but afterwards through the murmuring and unthankfulneſſe of the people, it was either bitter to them, or it had no ſavour. I believe the time was, when ſuch a publick bleſſing as this, (yea much inferior to this) was counted ſweet: you could raſte then how good God was to his people, in giving them victories; but now ſuch Mercies are either bitter, or you feel no ſavour in them: Sirs, you may thank your ſelves for this change: For the truth is, your great murmurings and unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe againſt God and man, hath brought you into this unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and ſad condition.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Methinkes in this victory you ſhould ſee the ſnare and pit before you. <hi>Milo Crotoniatas,</hi> whilſt he was tearing aſunder the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165354:6"/>ſtock of an Oke, his ſtrength ſayling him, the cleft ſuddenly clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, was ſo held faſt by the hands that he became a prey to the Beaſts of the feild. You have been a long time trying to teare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder this Common-wealth, and great hope you had, that <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> with the Rebels there would work wonders for you, but you ſee that ſtrength now failes you, take heed then, leaſt the cleft cloſe, and you are held faſt by the neck.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This victory gives me an occaſion to remember that ſaying of <hi>Solomon; Who ſo rewardeth evill for good, evill ſhall not depart from his houſe,</hi> Pro. 17.13. Howſoever, theſe men will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that they are beholding to the Parliament and Army, for their preſent peace, libertie, livelihood, yet the thing is ſo: yea more, under God, by their care and wiſdome, theſe raſh and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy men, were kept from bondage and ſlavery, into which they (poore fooles) moſt willingly and greedily would have thruſt themſelves. It is reported of one <hi>Balthazar Gerard</hi> (who named himſelfe <hi>Francis Guyon</hi>) that with the money which the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> gave him for his reliefe, he bought piſtols, powder and ſhot, and therewith killed the Prince: The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (I mean not the moderate and ſober ſort) would ſerve our Governours and Souldiers ſo, even murder them if they could, for purchaſing libertie and peace for them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The backſlider</hi> (ſaith the Wiſeman) <hi>ſhall be filled with his own wayes,</hi> Pro. 14.14. What generation of men are more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted then theſe, from their own grounds and former Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: For have they not deſired, that <hi>Ireland</hi> might be relieved, and that the Proteſtant bloud ſhed there, might be revenged upon the barbarous Rebels? But behold their Apoſtacie, when they ſee this don, they vex and murmure at it; and are ſo much the Lord outragious and invective againſt the State, by how much the Lord bleſſeth our Forces there, and honours them with ſucceſſe and great victory. Tame foxes if they breake looſe, and turne wilde, do ten times more miſchiefe then thoſe, that were wilde from the beginning. It is very remarkeable, that none of the malignant Miniſters thorow-out the Land, who have from firſt to laſt held with the King, ſpeake ſo ſeditiouſly, or rayl ſo groſſely againſt the Parliament and Army as theſe men doe; theſe men, I ſay, who were once tame and ſtood for both, but are now broken looſe, and turnd wild.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:165354:7"/>
            <p n="7">7. Theſe great victories which God gives the Parliament, ſhould cauſe your hearts to ſmite you, to conſider how by your ſeditious doctrine many poore and ignorant people are brought to the ſlaughter, whoſe bloud one day will be required at your hande. The cruelties and infamies of <hi>Caligula</hi> are imputed to the Nurſe that gave him ſuck, which being cruell and barbarous of her ſelfe, rubbed the ends of her breſts with bloud, cauſing the childe, to whom ſhee gave milke, to ſuck them. Such cruell and inhumane nurſes are theſe men: inſtead of the ſincere milke of the Goſpel, they give their hearers the bloudy Tenents of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; ſo that the cruelties and infamies of the people, may be (at leſt in a great meaſure) imputed unto their Teachers: For no doubt the people would be willing to live a quiet and peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life under our preſent Government, but that theſe <hi>Sheba's,</hi> theſe ſons of <hi>Bieri,</hi> blow a Trumpet, to cauſe hurliburlies and commotions in the Land.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Seeing God hath made the Parliament ſo victorious, it would not be amiſſe (when you come to your ſelves) to conſider whether Chriſt or his Apoſtles have left you any precept or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to aſperſe that Government which is ſet over you. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde, either in Scripture, or other Hiſtory, that any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Jeſus Chriſt (for ſo you ſtile your ſelves) did ever before your time, meddle with civill Government, as to deny the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of that Government under which they lived. The abuſes of Magiſtrates, and their miſcarriages in Government, we grant Gods Miniſters have ſpoken againſt, (yet ſo, as alwayes obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving time, place, and other circumſtances, which you never doe) but the Government it ſelfe, whether Kingly, Ariſtocraticall, or Democraticall, they condemned not, neither medled with the change and alteration of ordinary Government, upon what ground or occaſion ſoever it was. So that there are two treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable crimes here charged upon you: firſt, that you are <hi>buſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies,</hi> as medling with things wherein you are not concern'd. Secondly, <hi>Falſe accuſers,</hi> in calling that State unlawfull, which is founded upon Scripture, Law, and Reaſon. Boyling liquor ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling above the brinks, fals into the fire, and comes to nothing: you are beſt beware, leaſt by riſing above your element you tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble down, and your names periſh.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:165354:7"/>
            <p n="9">9. It may be, upon the occaſion of this victory, you will be the more willing to take notice how the Malignants make uſe of you onely as <hi>Journeymen</hi> to ſerve their turne. Some write of the <hi>Jaccal,</hi> as he purſues his prey, barking like a dog, the Lyon meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the noyſe, followes it; now the <hi>Jaccal</hi> having wearied the Beaſt he chaſed, the Lyon that followed by the cry comes in, when he is at a bay, and takes from the other, what he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpent his time and labour about. Brethren, ſuppoſe by your bawling and barking at the preſent Government, you ſhould weary it, and bring it <hi>at a bay;</hi> doe yee thinke to have the prey? not in the leaſt; for the <hi>Royaliſts</hi> would take that from you, and not you, but the Prelates ſhould be eſtabliſhed, their Courts, Canons, Service-Booke, &amp;c. It is true, you knew in this caſe how to help your ſelves, namely, faces about, turn-coats, and as you were before; and ſo indeed you would fare better then the <hi>Jac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> have ſome of prey howſoever, with the Lion.</p>
            <p n="10">10. I would willingly know, when you are unpowring and <hi>ſpeaking evill of dignities,</hi> what people doe you thinke are pleaſed with ſuch vile and wicked ſtuffe. Methinkes you cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that in doing ſo, you <hi>make ſad the hearts of the righteous,</hi> and are no other, then ſervants to the baſe luſts of unholy and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men. The <hi>Indians</hi> have a fruit which they call <hi>Yogma,</hi> it fattens ſwine, but men loath it: The Idolater, Adulterer, Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, Drunkard, Sabbath-breaker, Atheiſt, Papiſt, &amp;c. delight to heare your rayling at the State; indeed they flock after you meerly for this <hi>Yogma:</hi> But I muſt tell you in the mean time, the godly of your own Congregations cannot abide it: ſo that by this meanes you looſe them, and are caſt out of their hearts and affections, though you ſeeme to gaine the favour and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of ſome Malignants.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In this looking-glaſſe, you may ſee two faces under one hood: you thinke to pleaſe the <hi>Royaliſts,</hi> by crying up <hi>a King, a King:</hi> and your brethren the <hi>Scots</hi> by crying out, <hi>The Covenant, the Covenant:</hi> but doe not cozen your own ſoules, for you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not any longer herein deceive rationall and knowing men: they perceive well enough your game and ayme: it is your outward pomp and worldly preferment that yee ſeeke after, under ſuch pretences. The Pope will have Kings and Princes to kiſſe his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165354:8"/>feet, and to draw them on, did uſe to have on his pantophile the Crucifixe or picture of Chriſt hanging on the Croſſe: that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth he would have reverence don unto. The truth is, you would faine be Popes, and have every man to kiſſe your feet; our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Councell of State, and the whole Nation bow down to you: and to draw them on, you tell ſome of a King, others of a Covenant, a meere cheat, for 'tis your feet you would have them kiſſe, ſubmit to your arbitrary power and lawleſſe will.</p>
            <p n="12">12. This ſeditious courſe of yours hath brought you already into a great ſtreight: And I believe, it will require ſome meetings at your <hi>Synon-houſe,</hi> to reſolve what to doe upon the Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving day neere at hand: If you obey the Parliaments Order, and keep the day, you know what the Cavaliers and Royaliſts will ſay of you: <hi>Neque fidei conſtans, neque ſtrenuus in perfidia:</hi> as it was ſaid of <hi>Claudius Apollinaris, A man that neither conſtantly kept his promiſe,</hi> (as you have not yours to the Parliament) <hi>nor ſtoutly maintained his treaſon,</hi> (as you not yours, if yee keep that day). Againe, if not, you know there is great danger in that. For howſoever upon the faſt day, for <hi>Ireland,</hi> you proudly contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Magiſtrate, and made it a day of recreation, yet I would not wiſh you to preſume now upon the like impunitie or indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. And if you fall into the hand of Juſtice, and ſo ſuffer, conſider before hand, what comfort you can take in ſuch ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</p>
            <p>Now it followes, that I ſpeake ſomething (as occaſioned by this victory) to <hi>Royaliſts</hi> and <hi>Cavaliers.</hi> Wee ſee by daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, if the coyn be good, men are contented to receive it from any hand: I ſhall not propound any thing to theſe men, but what is profitable and good for them, if the Lord be pleaſed to give them underſtanding hearts to embrace it, and make a right uſe thereof. Thunder (they ſay) falling upon a Serpent, takes not away the life, but her venome: The ſearcher of all hearts doth know my deſire is, ſo to apply this <hi>thundering-victory,</hi> as their malignity, obſtinacy, blindneſſe, &amp;c. may be removed, and they live happily, and in a comfortable and proſperous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider how ſuch as have engaged, and have been moſt active in the cauſe you ſtand for, have in the end (as the juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165354:8"/>of ſuch ſervice) undon themſelves, and brought ruine and miſery upon their wives and children. There is no Pilot in his right wits, when he ſees Sea-markes purpoſely ſet up to give warning of rocks, ſands, or ſhelves, will thereby take occaſion to run his veſſell upon them, but rather will imploy all his care and skill, that by avoyding them, he may eſcape the danger. To what end hath the Lord ſet before your eyes, the deſolation of many honorable and great families, the precious bloud of ſeverall thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands ſhed on a day; but to be a warning and caveat unto you, to keepe off from ſuch dangerous and deſtroying rocks, and not to run your ſelves vainly and fooliſhly, as they have don, into a way and courſe, which is neither honourable nor profitable for you. The bird will not fly into the net, or light on the lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, or run into the ſnare, when he ſees another bird flutter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her: The horſe as you are travelling will not follow the track of another horſe that ſticks faſt before you: you are men, and ſhould be rationall: Will yee then ſeeing others before you in the pit, fall likewiſe into the ſame? if you doe, you are the more to blame, and the leſſe to be excuſed. You know that leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>Foelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Methinkes by this time you ſhould perceive, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you ſtand for, is not good, and ſo much the Lord from time to time hath made knowne unto you by many cleare and plain demonſtrations. Take notice of the late King, how apparently God was againſt him; fought againſt him, curſt his bleſſings, ſcattered his counſels, ſo that nothing indeed proſpered under his hand. How dare yee then carry on the ſame worke, and his deſigne, knowing by former experience, in doing ſo the Lord will not proſper you. I cannot more fitly liken this generation of men, then to Bowlers, who having delivered their Bowl, uſe to follow it with bowing their body, to have it fall in towards the jack, but it keeps her bias, goes off, and runs another way. Much ſtrugling and ſtriving there hath been to bring the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt in, on the Kings ſide, no plots or deviſes have been wanting, what ſea and land could doe hath been don: but providence ſtill carried it another way, and this they ſaw, and could not but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the Lord was not with them, although they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, and ſtill doe in their froward and crooked courſes.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:165354:9"/>
            <p n="3">3. This <hi>victory</hi> gives me occaſion to put you in minde, how your principles and grounds are falſe, concerning formes of <hi>civill Government.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> living poorely in <hi>Egypt,</hi> thought no kinde of food better then <hi>Garlick and Onions:</hi> ſo you, having liv'd long under <hi>hingly Government,</hi> and not acquainted with a <hi>free State</hi> or Common-wealth, conceive <hi>Monarchie</hi> to be the beſt kinde of Government, which undoubtedly is the worſt: and my Reaſons for it are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The great <hi>Revenues</hi> which are waſted to maintaine this <hi>King ſhip, unuſefull Creature,</hi> a <hi>thing</hi> which the Land hath no need of, but can doe much better without it, (as Courts, Pallaces, Caſtles, Mannours, Parks, Forreſts, &amp;c.) if converted to a publick uſe, will be for the great profit and generall good of the whole Nation, poore and rich; whereas formerly, as imployed, did little ſervice, but fed Locuſts and Caterpillers, who deſtroyed the people.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How chargeable to a Kingdome are Kings children, through their pride, pompe, and exceſſive riot? and what is expected from them for all this? truly, if they be not a curſe and plague to the Nation, men thinke it a mercy, as for comfort and profit they expect none. Now how many Orphans and poore children by ſuch charges might be charitably and largely relieved, and would bleſſe God for it; whereas the others devoure all, without ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Sirs,</hi> we thanke you: as if they were not at all beholding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When corruptions and abuſes break forth, they are eaſier and ſooner ſuppreſt in a <hi>free State,</hi> then in the other. For 1. As they have their originall and riſe uſually from the Court, ſo the King (as we have had experience) will ſeek to defend the ſame. 2. Put caſe, the King hath no hand in ſuch abuſes (which would be a ſtrange thing) nevertheleſſe, conſidering he ſees and heares with other mens eyes and eares, they are not eaſily or thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reformed. But in a Common-wealth well ſetled, it cannot be ſo.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is ſeldome ſeen in a <hi>Monarchie,</hi> but the Officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State, are corrupt men, choſen by Princes, not for the publick good, but to ſerve their turne and intereſt. Whereas in a Common-wealth, the people chooſing their own Magiſtrates,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165354:9"/>are carefull to chooſe ſuch as ſhall doe juſt and right things for them. Beſides, If Magiſtrates be corrupt, the people can ſooner helpe themſelves by removing them, and chooſing better, in a <hi>free State,</hi> then under Kings.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In no Common-wealth is there ſuch ſufferings of good men, innocent bloud ſpilt, unlawfull and unneceſſary warres rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, intolerable taxes impoſed, undue and illegall courſes taken, as where Kings doe reigne.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That muſt be beſt, which is <hi>a mean</hi> between two extreames, and thus is a <hi>free State,</hi> between <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Anarchy:</hi> that one ſhould rule alone, is againſt the common Maxime; <hi>Plus vident oculi quum oculus;</hi> two eyes ſee more then one. Againe, that none ſhould governe, or all, is abſurd and ſenceleſſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is rightly obſerved by <hi>Bodin; Wee commonly ſee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the changing of Princes, new deſignes, new lawes, new Officers, new friends, new enemies, new habits, and a new forme of living: For Princes take delight to change and alter all things, that they may be ſpoken of, which doth many times cauſe great inconveniences, not onely to the Subjects in particular, but alſo to the whole body of the State.</hi> De Rep. l. 6. cap. 4. But no ſuch prejudice or perill is incident to a Common-wealth, if any thing be publickly altered, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely don, and upon good ground, and for the generall profit and ſafety of the people.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In a well governed Common-wealth, great men as well as others, are encouraged unto the ſtudy of vertue, wiſdome, Juſtice, becauſe there, not titles or birth-right, but abilities and good parts make them capable of preferment: in ſuch a <hi>State</hi> there is no door open to come into places of authoritie, by bribery, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, friendſhip, but as men are fitted and gifted. Whereas in Kingdomes men come to have Offices and preferment by ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; a foole, or a knave, will challenge authoritie by being the <hi>Kings coſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. We know by experience, that in all ages the Goſpel and way of Chriſt hath been moſt withſtood and oppoſed under Kings. As on the contrary, in Common-wealths the ſame hath found greateſt favour, furtherance, and enfargement: And hence it is, that our <hi>Pulpit-Incendiaries,</hi> with their brethren the <hi>Scots,</hi> cry out ſo much for a King; they well know ſuch a forme of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165354:10"/>is fitteſt for them, and will beſt ſerve their turne, whereby to ſuppreſſe the truth, perſecute the Saints, under the name of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> and to erect a forme of will-worſhip, forcing all both ſmall and great, rich and poore, free and bond, to fall down and worſhip their Image, if not, neither buy nor ſell, but kild for hereticke.</p>
            <p>In the writing of theſe things, it makes me call to minde the condition of the people in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> living in a <hi>Free State,</hi> ſuch there, as are Papiſts among them, will not have the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to reigne againe over them, but deſire rather to be under the preſent Government: yea though they are Papiſts (I ſay) and have not libertie granted them for the free exerciſe of their Religion, yet by no meanes will heare of a King any more. And no doubt the like ere long will be the caſe of the people of this Land, when they have once taſted the ſweetneſſe of a <hi>Free State</hi> (as I hope they will every day more and more) and have their preſent grievances and taxes taken off, every man enjoying his own without moleſtation, and have juſtice ſpeedily don them, they will no more deſire a King to Rule over them. And to have it ſo, the way is, for every one to ſubmit to the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, live peaceably, and doe what he can, that all things may be effectually and well ſetled amongſt us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly; it is not poſſible that this victory ſhould doe you good, or any counſell given you from the occaſion of it, ſo long as you make <hi>lyes your refuge,</hi> yea delight to be encouraged and ſtrengthened in falſhood: doe not many of you, take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in ſcurrilous and baſe Pamphlets, and by reading the filthy and ſcandalous things in them, are hardened in your dangerous and bad condition? I have read ſome-where, when the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Avidius Caſſius</hi> opened a Cheſt, which they found in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo's</hi> Temple at <hi>Seleucia,</hi> that there came forth ſuch an infection, as thereby they were all poyſoned and kild. If you will not be murdered, then look not into their venemous and abhorred Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, for theſe villaines onely ſtudy, how by lyes, ſlander, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniation, to make you diſ-affected to the State, and act againſt it, and ſo to be undon in body, ſoule, and eſtate. They which hawk for birds, doe of purpoſe make a ſtale of the Owl, for whileſt the ſillie birds come flocking and ſtaring about her, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165354:10"/>they are taken: The <hi>Libeller</hi> againſt the State, is the <hi>Devils Owl,</hi> whilſt the fooliſh and ſilly people are looking upon him, and hearkning to him, he takes them in his ſnare, and holds them faſt. I ſhall ſay no more but thus; <hi>A prudent man foreſeeth the evill, and bideth himſelfe: but the ſimple paſſe on, and are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Prov. 22.3.</p>
            <p>As for Papiſts, it is to be fear'd, they will make no good uſe of this great <hi>victory:</hi> but as a furious maſtiff is the madder for his chaine: and iron hardens under the hammer: ſo the Angel of God, now powring out his Viall upon the <hi>ſeat of the Beaſt and his Kingdome,</hi> will cauſe them the more <hi>to blaſpheme the name of God, his tabernacle, and them that dwell in heaven.</hi> Neither indeed may wee wonder, that ſuch wofull blindneſſe hath overtaken them, conſidering they are given up, by divine juſtice to the luſts of their own hearts, and to ſtrong deluſions. Beſides, the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable doctrines which they embrace, puts them forward to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Nevertheleſſe, upon this occaſion, ſomething we will ſay, concerning them; leaving the iſſue to God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They may clearly ſee, the Lord is now making inquiſition for bloud, &amp; the day of recompence is at hand; <hi>They have ſhed the bloud of Saints, &amp; of Prophets, &amp; thou haſt given them bloud to drink, for they are worthy.</hi> Green wood which is long in kindling, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues longer then the dry, if it have once taken fire: The Lord hath a while forborne to revenge the horrid cruelties of that barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſavage Nation, but now he is fallen in amongſt them, and <hi>woe, woe, woe, to the Inhabitants.</hi> As the <hi>Galli-Senones,</hi> after they had laid <hi>Rome</hi> waſt, were ſo overthrown, that their name was not left in the world: So it may be, that the memory of ſuch an inhumane and cruell Nation ſhall be bloued out from under heaven. Wolves and Foxes make many turnings forward and backward, run into brakes and briers, hide under buſhes, fly from one ſtarting hole to another: but all will not ſerve the turne, the dogs follow inceſſantly, and never give over till they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them, and devoure them: So <hi>evill purſueth, ſinners,</hi> even the <hi>Iriſh-ſinners,</hi> thoſe Rebels, murderers, monſters, monſtrous Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, I know not what to terme them; the Lord (I ſay) hath now ſet his judgements after thoſe Wolves, and it is not their bogs or woods that ſhall ſave them <hi>from the wrath of the Lamb,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:165354:11"/>but they ſhall become as dung for the earth, and their hope as the giving up of the Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither let them expect reliefe from other places; as for their <hi>new King,</hi> and his adherents, they ſhall ſtand either a farre off, for feare of their torments, ſaying, <hi>alas, alas;</hi> or what aſſiſtance and ayd ſoever they have, it ſhall but adde to their plagues, and further their deſtruction. As a wee ſack, wherein a naked man is covered, is ſo far from defending him againſt the cold, as it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth his ſhivering; ſo their helpe from others will prove their greater ruine. <hi>Ormond</hi> and <hi>Inchiqueen,</hi> the two Apoſtates, may ſhortly expect the juſt reward of perfidious traytors.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Raro antecedentem ſceleſtum</l>
               <l>Deſeruit pede poena claudo.</l>
               <l>Seldome Revenge, though ſlow of pace,</l>
               <l>Leaves ill foregoing men to trace.</l>
            </q>
            <p>As the <hi>Egyptians</hi> going after the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> as they paſſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the <hi>Red-ſea,</hi> could not but behold their death before them: So theſe men in lifting up their hands againſt this State, may ſee (if they were not ſtupid and ſenceleſſe) they are <hi>dead man,</hi> and that God will put them to ſhame, and confound them for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What men (unleſſe given over to a reprobate ſence) would not plainly apprehend, that the Lord hath a quarrell againſt them, hates their perſons, their courſe and cauſe; to conſider the time, when they were ſcattered: namely, when they were grown into a numerous body, by uniting the <hi>falſe Scots,</hi> and <hi>Renegado Engliſh,</hi> with the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> When all <hi>Munſter</hi> was theirs, all <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naught</hi> loſt, and all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> except <hi>Derry,</hi> and <hi>Lempſter,</hi> even to <hi>Dublin.</hi> When all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in <hi>Ireland</hi> was reduced and ſhut up in thoſe two townes, and the latter ſtreightly befieged by 19000 men, according to their own accounts. <hi>Then the Lord look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down from beaven</hi> (as the Parliament in their Declaration have piouſly expreſt) <hi>the habitation of his holineſſe, and his glory, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated them; Then he ſent forth his wrath and conſumed them as ſtubble or as chaffe before the winde.</hi> And here I chalenge, all Papiſts, Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts, and Malignants, to produce, if they can, the like example, where and when, <hi>Jebovob Iireh,</hi> God was ever ſo ſeen in the Mount for them, and appeared even ſo miraculouſly, ſince the warres began. <hi>Who ſo is wiſe will obſerve theſe things:</hi> But, <hi>A bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165354:11"/>man knoweth not, neither doth a foole underſtand this.</hi> As he that will not goe out of darkneſſe cannot ſee the ſhining light of the Sunne: So the Papiſts, unleſſe they come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe, death, and hell, they will not obſerve, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed can they, the works of God, though they ſhine and are as cleare as the Sun at noone day.</p>
            <p>We may not (upon this occaſion) altogether forget our <hi>deare</hi> Brethren in <hi>Scotland;</hi> Now a word is enough to the wiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We underſtand that this victory is not very welcome to them, and no marvaile, for it tends not to the advancement of their Intereſt here in <hi>England,</hi> and they ſee, whom they curſe, God bleſſes. It hath been their endeavour a long time, that our Magiſtrates ſhould perſecute Gods people. <hi>Their lawes</hi> (ſay they,) <hi>are divers from all people; neither keepe they the Kings lawes, therefore it is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them.</hi> And as <hi>Haman</hi> prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo far with <hi>Abaſuerus,</hi> as there was an <hi>Act</hi> made and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Church and people of God ſhould be deſtroyed; yet afterward by a mighty hand of providence were preſerved and honoured; ſo that Nation (with others) wrought with our State, that ſomething was don, for the ſuppreſſing of many godly and faithfull Chriſtians: inſomuch, as they deſpaired of life, liberty, ſafety: but God (who <hi>abhorres the bloudy man</hi>) fruſtrated their purpoſes. The truth is, our Governours have had ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, of the fidelity, truſt, and conſcientiouſneſſe of ſuch men, whom they brand for Sectaries, and of many victories and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances under God by them, as they cannot hearken any more to their Antichriſtian and bloudy counſell: neither will they be brought into a ſnare by their general humiliations ſo often talk'd of. The Wolfe ordinarily waſheth his mouth after he hath prey'd, leſt he ſhould be diſcovered by the colour of his bloud: It is worth the noting, when the <hi>Scots</hi> have aſperſed our Nation, and urged the State to perſecution, immediatly they cry, <hi>a faſt, a faſt,</hi> as if ſuch innocent bloud were wip'd off by hypocriticall faſting.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The modeſty and patience of our State, is much to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd; being ſo often provok'd and occaſioned by the <hi>Scots,</hi> that they ſay nothing in relation to the condition of that people. For otherwiſe they might ſoon ſtop their mouthes, and put them to ſhame and ſilence for ever. They cry out againſt <hi>England,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165354:12"/>of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> as <hi>Separatiſts, Browniſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> &amp;c. But ſuppoſe there are ſuch, yet theſe <hi>Independents,</hi> are not <hi>falſe,</hi> not <hi>lyers, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, flatterers, deceivers, ſwearers, drunkards, whoremaſters, and irreligious and prophane perſons,</hi> as it is well knowne who are ſuch, for the generality and greater part of the Nation. Now is it not better and more for the ſafety of a Common-wealth, to have therein, men, known to be faithfull, juſt, true, upright, religious: then a kinde of people who are neither honeſt nor godly, neither make conſcience of what they doe or ſay?</p>
            <p n="3">3. This victory, it may be, will cauſe our brethren to keepe at home, and meddle no more with us; but leave our <hi>State</hi> to order thier own affaires. An Aſſe will not goe by a pen or place where ſhe once fell: I know they have not forgotten the place where they fell: I doe not ſay like <hi>Aſſes:</hi> onely under favour I may ſay, they will ſhew themſelves little better, if they come againe into the ſame place and caſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But how comes it to paſſe, that ſince this <hi>victory,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> complain of great perſecution in <hi>England:</hi> and that their <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian brethren</hi> here ſuffer exceedingly for the truth. Some chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren will teare &amp; ſcratch their Mother in the face, and then cry, as if they had been beaten or abuſed; whereas there is nothing don to them, but onely they wronged their Mother. The men for whom the <hi>Scots</hi> are now praying, as under ſad and heavy ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, they revile the Magiſtrates, deſpiſe their Government, ſet at nought their lawful and juſt commands, and ſtirre up the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to rebellion: and then cry out, <hi>Perſecution; ah how their mouths are ſtopt, they cannot deliver the whole counſell of God, their forefathers were never under the like Tyrants,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas there was nothing in the world don to them, but onely they abuſed the State.</p>
            <p>Before I conclude, a word or two, to that noble <hi>Jones,</hi> and the victorious Souldiers with him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There was a law among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> if any man were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of a benefit, he might be cald to Law, and found ſo, was puniſhed for it: We are very ſenſible of the bleſſing which the Lord hath given us by your hands; wee are thankfull to God, mindfull of you, and doe deſire to <hi>Improve the mercy</hi> in the beſt way and manner we can. The <hi>Jewes</hi> uſe to ſay, of him that hath don any memorable thing for his Nation; <hi>Zicrono libraca; Bleſſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165354:12"/>be his memory:</hi> your memory amongſt us is bleſſed, your names precious, and all well-affected people love and honour you. <hi>Si omnes qui reip: conſulunt, cari nobis eſſe debent: certe inprimis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratores, quorum conſilijs, virtute, periculis, retinemus &amp; noſtram ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; imperij dignitatem.</hi> Cic. de Orat. lib. 2. If all thoſe that care and have the charge of the Common-wealth, ought to be deare unto us; then eſpecially ought our noble Captaines, by whoſe counſell, proweſſe, and perill, we maintain the eſtate and honour of our Countrey.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Generall,</hi> imployed in that ſervice, it doth appeare, he hath the parts and qualities of a right Commander. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Diodor. Sicul. <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in warre muſt look both forward and backward, and every way whence any danger or advantage is towards. They ought to know when to march, and to fight with advantage; where to imploy horſemen, where ſhot, and to underſtand the advantages of all ſorts of grounds; neither to be ignorant of any ſtratagem of warre.</hi> Liv. 9. Now in theſe particulars, and many more, hath <hi>Jones</hi> ſhewed himſelfe a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and gallant Souldier; neither may it be ſaid of him untruly or unfitly, what is written of <hi>C. Caeſar, in his actions be was moſt conſiderate, in hazard and danger moſt reſolve, in executions ſpeedie, oppreſſing his enemies many times before the coming of the newes were heard.</hi> Sueton. in vita Caeſ. So of <hi>Cato, in watchings and labour he went beyond the common Souldiers.</hi> Liv. 34. <hi>Monſtrabat tolerare la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores,</hi> as <hi>Lucan</hi> reports of the younger <hi>Cato</hi> in that painful march thorow the deſerts of <hi>Affrick, he by his patience and example ſhewed what others were to doe.</hi> As <hi>Valerius Corvinus</hi> uſed no other encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to his Souldiers then this; <hi>Facta mea non dicta ſequi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, nec diſciplinam ſed exemplum a me petere.</hi> Liv. 7. So hath <hi>Jones</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes encouraged his, ſaying, they ſhould imitate not his words but his deeds, and doe as they ſaw him to give them an example.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the reſt, whether Officers or private Souldiers: In this victory you may behold, how wonderfully the Lord hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured you for your fidelity to your Countrey: and becauſe you did not, when yee were low, and the enemy at the higheſt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Parliament, or your truſt, as others baſely did, who ſince have ſeen and felt the revenging hand of God upon them for it. And no doubt, this great deliverance will not a little encourage
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165354:13"/>you, and the reſt of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> there, to ſtand firme and faſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the <hi>Iriſh Rebels,</hi> not only to revenge the Proteſtant bloud, which they have ſhed in a villanous and barbarous ſort: but alſo for the ſafety of your Countrey, your families, friends, wives, children, kindred, and what elſe may be thought precious and deare to you. For the heads of the Rebels there, as <hi>Rupert, Ormond, Inchiqueen,</hi> &amp;c. intend further then our loſſe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> they ſeek the ruine and overthrow of <hi>England,</hi> even our perſons, eſtates, yea and our ſoules too. <hi>Dulce &amp; decorum eſt pro patrio mori.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>It is a ſweet and noble Gaine,</l>
               <l>In Countreys quarrell to be ſlaine.</l>
            </q>
            <p>King <hi>Leonidas</hi> comforted himſelfe and three hundred more of his ſervants, who were killed at <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mopilas,</hi> fighting for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Countrey, as appeareth by <hi>Simonides</hi> his Greek Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph, turned into Latine by <hi>Tully,</hi> thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dic hoſpes Spartae, nos te hic vidiſſe jacentes,</l>
               <l>Dum ſanctis patriae legibus obſequimur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Laſtly, to cloſe this Diſcourſe: As wee have ſhewed how this <hi>Mercy ſhould be improved</hi> at home, ſo we hope our Army there, will uſe this victory to purpoſe, and be carefull ſtill to maintaine that which they winne. <hi>Vincere ſcis Annibal, victoria uti neſcis;</hi> as <hi>Maberbal</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannibal,</hi> he was not ſo well able to make uſe of his victories, as to obtaine them. <hi>Caeſar</hi> having obtain'd a great victory againſt the <hi>Helvetians, ceaſed not to purſue the remainder ſo long, untill all yeelded.</hi> And afterward having foyled <hi>Vereingetorix</hi> in the feild, and cauſed him to retyre with the reſt of his Armie, <hi>He did not leave him untill be bad forced him to take Alexia for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence:</hi> nor then neither, untill ſuch time he had the town, and all within yeelded to his mercy. <hi>Vanquiſhing Pompey in open field, he would not ſuffer him to take Sanctuary in his campe, but drove him thence, and reſted not, untill he had taken his flight, nor before the reliques of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie that fled to the hils neer by, had yeelded, being cut from water.</hi> Three things ought to be don when an Army is victorious. 1. Not to ſuffer the enemy to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther head, but to ſcatter his forces. 2. To befiege the chiefe Citie, and to ceaze the Countrey into their hands, not ſuffering the enemy in any place to reſt. 3. The Generals care ought to be, how to take off the enemies ſubjects from them, and to deprive them of the ayd of their Confederates. A matter eaſily don, if he proceed wiſely in warre and juſtly after the victory. For as good ſucceſſe procureth the Conquerour friends: ſo men are ready to abandon and forſake ſuch as are overcome. Now for the good will of him that dwelt in the Buſh, let the bleſſing be upon the head of our Army.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
